[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software for software engineering radio
this is Sam tager and I'm here today
with my guest Jason C McDonald Jason is
a software development manager speaker
and the author of dead simple python
among books he's the founder of Mousa
media which is an open- Source software
organization where he trains software
development interns so Jason and I are
here today to talk about something he's
developed called Quantified tasks which
is a replacement or alternative for
story points so Jason let's start with
talking about story points what they are
where they came from what people use
them for sure yeah happy to be here Sam
so story points comes from the agile
methodology that is it came out of the
agile methodology specifically scrum and
the idea was to be able to estimate how
long it was going to take to accomplish
a particular task or release as soon as
I say how long of course all the agile
purists are screaming no it's not about
time which that's the goal is it's not
supposed to be about time but in
practice when you implement scrum when
you implement story Point estimation in
an organization that is what it becomes
about because managers want to know how
long is it going to take us to ship this
code so story points was devised as a
way of measuring how much effort it was
going to take to accomplish a certain
goal a certain task but because we don't
have something like inches or Pounds or
hours or some sort of Handy metric that
we can use to measure the size of a task
they instead decided to measure it kind
of in the Imperial way you think back
before we had the standard metrics
everything was measured relative to
something else and usually the king's
foot in through throughout Europe Aro
the imperial measurement of the foot so
story points is a way of measuring tasks
relative to other tasks so you come up
with some fairly arbitrary scheme of
numbers you have one task you you give
it a number it almost doesn't matter
what number you give that first task and
then you measure everything else in
relation to that task is it bigger or is
it smaller which is an interesting idea
but like with the foot in Imperial times
it lacks standardization it lacks
repeatability it lacks objectivity as
soon as you change Kings or in this case
teams your measurements are suddenly
very different yeah well I remember
reading the book The agile Samurai by
Jonathan rasmason I think that's the
right author's name and it had something
in there where it talked about how from
psychology we're really good at
measuring looking at two things and
telling which one's bigger right so that
relative measuring we're pretty good at
but the absolute measuring of saying
okay this one's bigger than that but
which On's is this 1.9 and this is 2.1
or like what it's a lot harder to do
that yes exactly so I think that that's
some of the psychology behind it so what
scales do people usually use for these
like I've seen all kinds of stuff from
like numbers F Fibonacci sequences
t-shirt sizes have you seen anything
else or are those pretty much those are
basically in a nutshell anytime you're
dealing with a numeric scale what's
preferred to something with some sort of
exponential or at least nonlinear growth
that's why Fibonacci is so popular and
it's funny we say Fibonacci because it's
not Fibonacci it's usually a modified
Fibonacci Sequence where they add a
number they they drop something I can't
remember exactly what but they they've
modified the Fibonacci sequence to be a
cleaner exponential curve and it's the
idea being that the larger the number is
the more distance there should be
between that and the next number the
reason for that being the larger the
task the more likely is there's
something uncertain in there something
you don't know or you don't understand
so a difference between a task that'll
take you 10 minutes and a task that's
going to take you an hour or between a
Fibonacci 1 and a Fibonacci 2 is very
small but the difference between a task
that's going to take you and again I
know everyone's cringing that I'm using
time here but again that's what it
ultimately boils down to a task that's
going to take take you a week versus a
task is going to take you two weeks
there's a huge difference between the
two because you don't know what other
things you don't know you don't know
what you don't know the more complicated
the task the more effort involved the
more unknowns there probably are
probably massive asteris K which is
again where things get a little bit
wibbly wobbly timey wiy yeah what I
always talk about estimates and stuff I
always try to think plan on really short
intervals a short interval you plan on
the more certainty you can have like if
I wake up in the morning say this is
what I'm going to do today I can be
fairly certain about that if I say this
is what I'm going to do next week well
there's a lot of time that passes
between now and then and a lot of you
know I could get interrupted I my plans
could change completely right short
Cycles being one of the key principles
of agile so my next question is what do
the current approaches approaches fail
to capture like you created this
alternative what why did you create this
alternative well and I have to go off on
a it briefly too when I created this
system I did not create it on the basis
of replacing story points in fact when I
created this originally I didn't even
know story points existed because I
conceived of this while reading the book
dreaming in Code by Scott Rosenberg back
during my first year as a software
engineer I read this book and there is
this remark in there by Scott Rosenberg
that there are certain tasks which he
refers to as black holes which just suck
up inordinate amounts of time and it
doesn't matter how much work you throw
at it it never seems to get done and he
said every project has one of these more
than likely and the more of these you
have in a project the less lik of the
Project's ever going to get finished
most famously in his book He pointed to
the disaster of the FAA trying to get a
new air traffic controller system built
that never did get built because it was
full of those black holes
but he made an interesting remark that
most software Engineers can tell you
whether or not a task is a black hole
within the first 10 minutes of working
on it so that created planted the seed
in my mind that okay there's something
about a task that we're capable of
assessing there is something objective
here that can tell us whether or not
this task can even be completed in a
reasonable span of time if at all and so
that began this process of me developing
what would iteratively become Quantified
tasks what became evident as I started
working on teams that use scrum that use
story points was that what story points
was failing to capture was not only this
probability that the task was a black
hole it was being sort of indirectly
captured by the size of the Fibonacci
number but not reliably maybe that eight
is a black hole maybe not like those
numbers all of this thought was going
into them I was hearing all these
conversations about oh well there's lack
of documentation on this or oh that code
is really bad or you know we're not sure
how this particular technology works or
that requirements document isn't fully
finished so there's all these factors
that were going into the sizon
conversation but none of that
information was being captured so you
would have two tasks that would be an
eight and the eight would have been
arrived at by completely different
criteria one just lacked documentation
maybe a lack of Precedence and the other
had some some sort of really snarly
complexity that we didn't know how to
untangle and yet none of that
information was in that estimate which
made it very hard to tell how accurate
that eight was or who should even take
on the task yeah I think that probably
stems from the problem of different
people doing the estimating than
necessarily doing the task or maybe if
you have a big backlog you know you
estimate you throw in the backlog and
then you know it's several months before
you actually get to it or weeks or
whatever exactly I could see that
causing problems because estimation is
very subjective and it's individual so
every team has their own scale as it
were and you could have six teams that
all use the exact same Fibonacci scale
and you can't compare their tasks you
can't compare across because they're
using different criteria and chances are
they never wrote down what those
criteria are and even if they did
they're probably not going to agree with
that well we a different and eight means
something different to us because of
this unique facet of our team and that
can even happen within a project you
lose half your team gain some new
developers now your estimations are
completely different so you can no
longer even size to the earlier task in
your own project yeah I've heard someone
once say like if you change a member of
your team you have a whole new team
which I thought was a very interesting
comment yes my staff Mentor at canonical
Pat VOR once remarked to that every time
you add someone to a team the team's
shape changes because the individual and
the team both adapt to the unique
attributes and traits of the individual
you're
adding great so Quantified tasks has
these multiple numbers right so in story
points you just have one number which
fails to capture the stuff so how do the
different numbers and story points what
are they and how do they capture this
Nuance right so there are three facets
of Quantified tasks I have to clarify
that up front so there's a Triad of
numbers that are related to planning and
then there's a pair of numbers that are
related to stability and bugs and we can
come back around to those but the Triad
of numbers that I'm focusing on here for
estimation are distance friction and
relativity the thing to understand is
that you capture these numbers
individually but then there's also a
very simple formula that is used to
derive an energy Point score and energy
points is the drop in replacement for
story points so I'm going to come back
around to energy points the three
numbers though are valuable even by
themselves they're the kind of the three
ways of measuring the effort involved in
a task one of the challenges with story
points is that we're measuring it
relative to our own skill rather
implicitly we look at it we think well
that would take
me a day well the problem is you may not
be working on that in fact you may not
even be at the company more anymore by
time someone is working on that so we
can't rely on that subjective personal
this is this size to me because of my
skill level we have to factor our skill
out of this and that's why I have these
three specific numbers
distance is how roughly how long would
it take me to complete this task if I
knew everything and that little Clause
is what takes subjective skill
differences out of the equation if you
knew everything how long would it take
you to complete this task this separates
out raw work fingers on keyboard just
implementing from closing any sort of
knowledge gaps that you may have either
as a developer or as a result of having
to invent so it isolates just that raw
work variable out and it's always
measured relative to your Sprint so
whatever size Sprint whatever size
development cycle your company uses that
is what distance is relative to because
time is not really the point here it's
raw work that you're measuring the
second number is friction which is how
many resources or I guess you could say
what what lack of resources is there to
help you complete this task again it's
not how much do I have to learn it's
what resources exist because it's going
to take significantly less developer
effort to complete a task that involves
reading some wellmaintained
documentation and a tutorial versus
having to read between the lines of an
API document that hasn't been maintained
in six years and inventing the rest
there's a massive difference in the
amount of work involved there the amount
of effort involved which by the way
measuring friction has the upshot that
it automatically surfaces all of your
lwh hanging fruit because low friction
tasks are great first contributor tasks
someone brand new to the team someone
who's brand new to the language can pick
that up because there's more resources
for them to figure it out and then your
more senior members can take the higher
friction tasks because they're going to
need that expertise to get it done the
third number then is relativity so
there's this saying in story pointing
make your best estimate multiply by
three and that works because that
multiplying by three is accounting for
everything you don't know well how much
you don't know is something you can
usually figure it out up front if you
look at a task you can go you know what
we have no idea how this tool works this
is complete invention here and I'm not
even sure this algorithm is possible in
this language now you have some unknowns
so relativity becomes this measurement
of of kind of a ratio of how much you
know versus how much you don't know
about the task itself how much that is
how much is obvious versus how much is
Discovery and invention and this becomes
your multiplying Factor when you create
your energy points so energy points you
get by adding your distance and your
friction scores which by the way forgot
to mention all of these are on a scale
of one to five so you add your distance
and friction scores together and then
you multiply by relativity which is
again one to five and that is going to
give you an energy Point score that
score by the way because you're using
three fixed and reasonably objective
systems for
measuring are repeatable across teams so
that number you're getting that energy
Point score you are getting is
comparable not only to every other
Quantified task estimated task in your
Project's history but to any other other
Quantified task estimated issue you've
ever worked on you actually can form a
personal relationship to that number
which makes it now directly useful
because like for me personally I
typically can complete about 23 to 26
energy points per Sprint if I know the
stack that holds true regardless of the
team I'm working on so that allows me to
tell you how long it's actually going to
take me to clear six story points I know
that that's actually a number I can give
and that allows for better selection of
work better distribution of work and
better time estimates for the managers
because we have this score that is
repeatable it's objective and we've
recorded the factors that went into it
the amount of work the amount of
research and the amount of innovation
that's going to go into it so for teams
that are using story points now is
dropping in Quantified tasks just simply
changing the way they come up with their
number is that basically it like using
these three numbers and then or is there
basically yeah yeah that literally is it
and the interesting thing is all the
teams have implemented this on and all
the teams I've talked to about this have
remarked that this is basically the
conversation that they're trying to have
about story points anyway but they
hadn't really boiled it down to those
three questions concretely so things
wind up drifting off into different
priority level see this takes the
question of what's more important what
you know what do I assign more weight to
in my estimate out of the equation
thereby removing that subjectivity that
varies from Team to team because we have
a formula and we have three one to five
numbers that really
constrains how you do estimations so now
estimation becomes in a team asking
those three questions how long would it
take relatively if you knew everything
how many resources are there
documentation health of the code
availability of subject matter experts y
yada and how much do we know versus we
don't know those three questions wind up
guiding the conversation during
estimation and it would sound like that
should take longer than story pointing
would but in practice it actually tends
to go faster because you've now laser
focused your conversation and everyone
can throw out their estimates and
specifically narrow in on what they
maybe disagree on and find the numbers
that everyone is comfortable with yeah I
can imagine spending less time arguing
yeah know I gave this a three you gave
it a five why right and then you could
explain a lot easier exactly very good
so for people who are using some common
tooling like maybe jir or I don't know
git laab issues or whatever or GitHub
issues or whatever do these things
support using Quantified tasks or
because Quantified tasks is a fairly new
method you're not going to be able to
fire up a tool and just find this like
sitting there waiting for you but most
issue trackers do have some form of
custom Fields jira especially works
really well with this because you can
add the custom fields for distance
frictional relativity and actually have
instructions at quantifi ask.org if
anyone wants to follow the the setup
process because jira integrates really
tightly with this so you set up the
fields for distance frictional
relativity and then you set up a jur
autom a task and once you fill in those
three Fields the Jura automation task is
going to run and it will go ahead and
calculate your energy Point score off of
those and automatically fill in that
field for you and I actually used this
on a team earlier this year that I was
leading and it worked very well for us
because it would take us usually about
30 seconds to estimate a task and we
would just fill in distance friction
relativity from the dropdowns and then
it would propagate our our energy points
which would then show up throughout the
system as a story point would as a story
Point estimate would if you're using
something that doesn't have custom
Fields it does get a little bit more
challenging so like get lab issues
unless you're paying for the ultimate
tier you're not getting custom fields or
any of that jazz you're not even getting
story pointing so in that situation if
you're finding yourself limited by a
lack of custom Fields I like to use
labels in that situation so GitHub get
lab discourse I actually have used
discourse as an issue tracker it
actually works pretty well but at that
point you create tags for your different
dis restriction of Relativity you just
create tags for for each of them tags or
labels but above all if you are missing
everything if you have no way of making
this work you can actually still use
whatever if your thing just has a spot
for story points and you have no way of
adding custom Fields just put put the
estimate at the top of the description
just put in and there's an official
notation for this so like you could put
like D3 F2 R3 which would be distance 3
friction 2 relativity 3 equals and then
whatever your energy Point estimate is
and then copy that estimate into your
story point field yeah there has to be a
place to put a description or something
in there somewhere least it's still
there captured somewhere exactly and
really that's the point yeah so when you
look at the one number then you actually
can figure out how it was derived I
think that that would exact useful yeah
which goes back to the point you
mentioned at the beginning you know
we've got two eights well why are they
eights and yeah yeah and the other
upshot of capturing this information by
the way is that it actually puts
stakeholders decision makers Etc
especially non-technical decision makers
in a position where they can actually be
useful now because
managers try to make sense of story
points and again they tend to do that by
equating it to time or to budget or
whatever but because energy points comes
from three clearly
defined
scales and those estimates are actually
captured in the task what winds up
happening is that if you'll have say a
manager who's saying you know how can we
speed up development well now you can
actually look at those numbers you can
actually look at oh you know what the
reason things take us so long is because
our friction is routinely very high but
we don't have a lot of seniors on the
team we need more seniors in the
technology we're using if we're going to
move faster or else we need to bring
down the the friction maybe we need to
use some technology that's better
documented so it gives a starting
position to have a conversation with
your non-technical contributors because
they don't have to understand code or
agile to understand how Quantified tasks
is working it's documented it's written
down yeah those are really good examples
I quite like that so one thing I I see
teams that are using story points they
often like to talk about velocity what
are your opinions on that how does that
work with Quantified tasks is that even
a useful metric it can be and I got to
thinking a lot about the value of
velocity and Quantified tasks on the
heels of that rather controversial
McKenzie article about measuring
developer productivity because one of
the reasons i' up with Quantified task
in the first place was because there was
no way of measuring developer
productivity because there was no way of
measuring how much energy went into a
task so because you can't measure the
work they're doing you can't measure how
productive they are it's kind of a bit
of a QED so if we understand the amount
of energy that goes in then it's easier
to understand how productive developers
are being the limiting factor
in software engineering is not time it
is not money it's rarely even technology
it is always developer energy if you're
out of steam no amount of money time or
additional team members is going to
increase the amount of energy you have
you're done you are out of energy for
the week this is why by the way the
saying never ship on Friday is so wise
it's not because there's something
special about Friday it's because people
are out of steam they have been working
all week their brains are tired
therefore they're more likely to make
mistakes so because energy points is
directly linked to developer
energy then velocity becomes a useful
way of measuring productivity in that
you are seeing how much energy your
developers are actually putting into
things how much they have available to
them you can start budgeting because you
know how much is available ailable too
your developers can say well you know I
usually get done with about 20 story
points a week well now you have a budget
and you know okay I can't throw 40
energy points at them and expect them to
get it done they're going to be out of
steam they have 20 energy points on
average to work with so those numbers
become a way of looking at the amount of
energy your team has over time and if
you're noticing a sudden drop off in
productivity sudden drop off in velocity
now the question is where's the
developer energy going is it going into
meetings is it going into non coding
related stuff you know we know what
their budget is they're consistently way
below budget right now what happened why
is it there and that becomes the
beginning it's always beginning numbers
are never the end of the conversation
they're only the beginning of a
conversation but it becomes the
beginning of a conversation H I'm see
you're trending way below your average
what's going on where's the energy going
how can we help you
yeah those are very useful
conversations so the next question I
have is and we've kind of hit on this a
little bit but like I guess what
problems have you noticed that quantifi
tasks solved that story points just like
Miss and I think part of it is what we
just talked about but are there other
things that you've noticed the main
thing really just is that that
repeatability moving the conversation
into developer energy I guess that's the
biggest thing is that story points
because it doesn't mean anything and
when I say that I'm actually quoting a
manual practitioners who say well the
nice thing about story points is they
don't mean anything well that doesn't
make them particularly useful for
planning so I can't just tell you that
my window is 47 flbs wide that means
nothing to you you can do nothing with
that information if I told you it was
say three feet wide now if you were
going to fix my window that would mean
something so if you're going to use a
measurement it needs to mean something
and it needs to mean the same thing to
each person that's using that thing
that's using that measurement it needs
to not be changing from company to
company or team to team or individual to
individual because then you just have
chaos imagine if every engineering firm
had their own tape measure their own
proprietary tape measure with their own
proprietary measurement system the chaos
that would ensue we would never be able
to build anything so the unitless of of
story points really works against
against not only because it's not useful
at that point but also human beings
especially
managers live to derive meaning out of
things humans don't like things that
mean nothing they assign meaning and if
there is no meaning they will invent a
meaning so story points is begging to be
misunderstood that's the problem it is
crying out to be interpreted but when
there's no interpretation every
interpretation manager is going to come
come up with is going to be wrong so by
having a system that has a meaning then
that is also going to resist
misinterpretation because you can't
pretend energy points is anything other
than measuring developer energy because
that's what it is it's not going to as
readily be misunderstood as a time
commitment or a budget
because it is about developer energy and
that's capped but since managers like
time and money because they're the
things they have control over this
number becomes useful to them because
they can go hm we're not moving very
fast but that's because this team
doesn't have enough energy to go faster
if we added a couple of senior Engineers
to this team maybe they would or if we
removed some meetings from their
calendar or if we put some money into
finding ways to improve how much energy
they have available to them maybe
shorter working days for example and so
they can start using the tools they have
money time policy to try to optimize how
much developer energy is available which
is honestly what we've been wanting them
to do all along right yeah that's great
so my next question is can you talk
about a specific project where they were
using story points you came in you
switched over to quantify task and how
did that go and did you learn any
lessons there yeah I'm trying to think
what's funny is can think of a couple of
projects where people didn't want to
switch and this was a little bit earlier
on I actually remember one project where
I had proposed this because the problems
they were running into was chiefly that
their estimates were both inaccurate and
useless and I proposed this and this is
actually the person who said to me well
I like story points because they don't
mean anything and I'm like
what and I think the problem there
becomes when story points become the end
instead of the means but and that was
literally the case here because this
person was actually publishing their
velocity charts online publicly as
marketing data as as a way of marketing
their company I'm like no you don't do
that well that's odd at the same time
that he says it's meaningless which is
just weird well it's meaningless and so
he was able to artificially inflate the
numbers and make it look like they were
more productive than they actually were
by
misrepresenting
velocity so Consulting house or
something right yeah ex yeah it was it
was and it was like it was just it was
scary so I I think one of the
interesting sides of this is because
Quantified tastic is not arbitrary and
it it's really hard to manipulate
because of its limitations its
deliberate limitations because like it's
really hard to manipulate inches for
example and inches an inch you can't
really manipulate that so I think it
helps expose some zombie scrum mindsets
where they're using agile for things
other than agile and I think it's where
you see some
resistance the team where I rolled this
out I actually was able to roll this out
at the beginning of the project so it's
not like we switched from story points
to energy points but everybody there had
been using story points up to that point
so they come into this project with a
story Point mentality and everyone's a
little bit skeptical like this is weird
I'm used to Fibonacci numbers why are we
doing this but they agreed to give it a
try and within one sizing session with
one planning session every single person
was sold because it's like I actually
know what this number means now the
funny thing is energy points follows
almost the same curve and range as the
Fibonacci
numbers so you could drop it in and just
add a casual glance at your board you
would not notice the difference so along
those lines when we talk about push back
do you tend get more push back from
management or from developers or is it
fairly equal I think it's fairly equal
because managers want information and I
remember one manager saying I don't want
to use this because I would rather
people write better descriptions and I
was trying to explain like well people
aren't going to write better
descriptions because developers are lazy
you know sorry what you literally pay us
to do is to be lazy we weaponize our
laziness into saving the company money
that's why we're here that's why you
hired us so develop ERS are lazy they
hate writing things down they hate
documentation they hate writing good
descriptions on tickets I rarely see
good descriptions on tickets any team
because no one wants to waste the time
at least they view it as a waste of time
so they don't do it so part of this is
about limiting how much writing they
actually have to do by capturing the
things that they should capture every
time so I think that's where this
manager didn't understand where this
would help because he just wanted more
text and wasn't really thinking about
well what are we capturing developers I
think are generally pretty open to it
unless they are members of The Cult of
agile as I refer to it because there's
agile methodology and then there's the
cult of agile and the cult of agile is
where it becomes a religion like I
mentioned earlier it is the end in
itself like the outcome of agile isn't
the point agile itself is the point we
do standups because we do standups we do
Retros because we do Retros and no one's
thinking about the outcome anymore and
where you have that there can be a lot
of resistance as well because this goes
against the
rituals it's going to the same end in
fact it's getting closer to the end that
you want but because it requires a bit
of a departure from kind of the
religious adherence to you know
Fibonacci numbers or t-shirt sizing or
what have you there can just be some
lack of familiarity kind of resistance
because people don't like new things
they don't like change but beyond that
honestly I haven't really run that much
resistance beyond that because if people
are doing story pointing for the goal of
sizing then this just becomes a way of
doing that quicker and more efficiently
so you mentioned something earlier about
how Quantified task can be used for
planning and estimation but also
something to do with bugs and volatility
and stability do you want to comment on
that yeah absolutely so leading into
this one thing I want to point out about
Quantified tasks is that every number in
there at least every number you set
directly is a 1 to five energy points is
a calculated number so that it isn't
constrained like that but every scale
you set is a one to five scale and fives
are always Special by the way in this
system a five is always special because
it means that there's something you need
to pay attention to so distance it means
this is going to take longer than a
Sprint break it down friction means we
know nothing about this like this is
just way too complicated we're going to
need to spike it to reduce some of the
lack of resources we have relativity 5
means this can't be completed in the
history of the universe just there's we
know nothing we know absolutely nothing
this is a black hole so FIV are always
special and I bring that up because that
applies to the volatility as well so I
can't take credit for the idea of
volatility this actually goes back to a
gentleman I was talking to on the dev
platform
dev.to he wrote a very interesting
article about that you could predict the
stability of a project by how long a bug
remained uncaught because if you think
about it we catch a very small fraction
of the bugs that are in our project so
if you catch 10 bugs then it's safe to
assume there's at least 10 more floating
around the reason that you can determine
this from how long a bug has been living
in your project is because it indicates
when you have a a quality control gate
as I like to call it that has failed
because we have these throughout the
software development life cycle you have
the design process where there should be
some discussion going on as you're
writing the requirements Etc there's the
coding process you should have code
review and static analysis tools and
tests QA should have additional testing
should have additional linters and what
have you and then you finally get to
production and then by that point you're
relying on your users to catch it so if
you have a bug that in design and makes
it to production what that means is that
your requirements review failed your
static analysis tools did not catch it
your testing didn't catch it your
linters didn't catch it your CI failed
to catch it your manual review failed to
catch it and now it landed in your users
lap so you have multiple points of
failure at this point so using that same
one to five strategy what you wind up
doing with this is that when you report
a bug you only record two numbers and
again they're one to fives you record
two numbers the origin which is what
point this emerged which is surprisingly
easy to figure out and your cut which is
when it was first
detected and you subtract those two
numbers and the resulting number tells
you which quality control gate
failed and the higher that average
volatility score is because when you
subtract the two that gives you
volatility the higher that average is
the more failures in your quality
control system you have and the more
likely you have bugs that are making it
in abroad okay so for these numbers like
what does the one to five represent one
is like it appeared in like the design
phase and then five is like my users
caught it is that the scale okay exactly
so they map to the software development
life cycle so one is planning two is
design three is implementation four is
verification and five is production okay
so if you catch a bug at the same phase
it originates you're great you have zero
volatility because bugs are always going
to show up but that means your quality
control is Flawless or at least darn
near close but if you have a high
average volatility then that is going to
tell you that you got no quality control
and all your Gates have failed and any
mistake you make in planning is going to
make it all the way out to the users huh
that's interesting you can also combine
this with one of the planning metrics
impact which I have talked about yet but
you can also combine this with impact to
tell you also the SE kind of the
severity that you're looking at because
cop minus origin times impact is going
to give you this number and actually
that's the actual volatility score
that's going to tell you not only if
your quality control gates are failing
but it's also going to tell you how
serious the bugs are that are
manifesting because you know honestly if
you have a bug that manifests as a
button that is one shade of blue off
that is nowhere near as important as the
bug where the user presses save and it
deletes everything in the record so that
impact also factors into the volatility
score okay so if I understand this
correctly it's almost like a risk score
the first number is like the likelihood
of something getting through right
because that's how long it existed and
you're multiplying that by the impact so
it's very much like a risk if you take
risk it's like probability times impact
kind of or probability consequence
exactly yep so by the time you take the
average across all the bugs in your
project which J can do this if you take
your average across all your bugs you've
got if you have a solution volatility
that's what that average is called the
solution volatility if that's greater
than 10 basically your servers are on
fire there you have some major problems
and you should probably stop shipping
features and figure out what the devil
is wrong with your pipeline because
nothing is reliable at that point okay
so I have one last question question is
there any time that you wouldn't
recommend this approach that You'
recommend like just sticking with story
points I have to be totally honest I
don't think I would ever recommend
sticking with story points because that
would be like recommending someone
measure everything relative to their own
foot versus using a ruler that said this
is not a Panacea this is a piece of the
puzzle but it's never going to be the
overarching solution to everything and
it fixes all of your problems and that's
not because Quantified tasks is somehow
insufficient for any given situation
it's because it isn't the whole solution
it's a piece of a solution if an
engineering firm has lots and lots and
lots and lots of problems with quality
control and planning and how they do
things but they switch from measuring
everything relative to the forman's foot
to using a ruler that's still an
improvement but it's not going to really
fix the rest of the problems in the
organization so it's like with agile in
general a lot of companies erroneously
think you can just throw agile
ceremonies at a project and it will
magically fix all the problems but what
has to change first is the mentality not
only of the developers but also with
managers of switching from this
waterfall technique of let's just plan
everything and make everything
predictable and all of that to switching
to an iterative approach of agile and
then agile is useful but without that
mindset shift it's really not going to
do much if any good in fact it'll
probably do harm and quantify Tas the
same thing yes you can implement it in
place of story points but if you're
already doing zombie scrum if you're
already misusing agile this is not going
to fix all of your problems so I think
teams need to look very carefully at why
they're having
problems and really take a hard look at
where the mindset needs to shift and
then use this as one of the tools to
help shift mindset help shift approach
but it needs to be secondary to that
introspection not first okay now would
implementing qualified tasks and though
perhaps help like indicate some of the
problems like It'll point out some of
the problems or is that it can in theory
but I think again if teams are using
yeah like I mentioned earlier you know
it can indicate when you're using zombie
scrum because there's this General
resistance to it
but it can be misused like anything else
can be misused good heart's law still
stands which is that as soon as you make
a metric a goal the metric ceases to be
useful so if a company were to adopt
Quantified tasks and suddenly make
lowering the energy Point estimates on
everything to be the goal then this is
not going to be useful because good
heart's law is going to completely
undermine it and estimates are still
just going to be a meaningless exercise
in futility as opposed to a planning
tool so you still have to look at where
your mindset is off as a team as a
company before you start throwing
Solutions at it but I think it's true as
a rule like we never fix a car by
throwing a wrench at it you can throw
every wrench in your toolbox at a car
and it's not going to fix the car if you
haven't identified what the problem is
once you know what the problem is
wrenches are very useful and in fact
it's probably impossible to fix many
problems without a Good Wrench but if
you don't know what the problem is the
wrench is just going to get in the way
okay yeah that's a great explanation
thank you very much so if people want to
learn more about this there is a website
right quantifi ask.org is that correct
yes y absolutely so I try to post
articles periodically on how to
implement this but if you go to that
website right along the top are the tabs
for planning estimation and stability
and that explains how to use each
section of Quantified tasks and don't
feel like you have to implement this
whole thing right now on your team one
of the cool things about this is that
you can just take one piece of this one
part that your team is going to find
useful Implement just that and you're
still going to get value out of it don't
feel like you have to rebuild your
entire issue tracker tomorrow to
implement this you can go gradually I
really recommend using this in the
context of that iterative agile approach
let your team take ownership of this
because if you just enforce it from the
top No One's Gonna like it yeah that's a
very good principle to live by so thank
you very much Jason thank you for
software engineering radio this is Sam
tager thanks for joining
us thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for
listening